Now in this lecture we want to look at three AWS services to assist with governance and regulation
compliant. So we will discuss these services on a higher level. So the first one is AWS
config. So AWS config, monitor and record config changes for AWS resources such as S3,
EC2 and almost all AWS services within your account. So in simple terms what AWS
config does is now let's say there's a security policy within your organization that none
of the S3 buckets should have public access. And you create a new S3 bucket which has public
access. So what AWS config is going to do is it's going to discover that S3 bucket as an inventory
item and reviewed against the organization policies that you have set in the AWS config.
And if it finds it non-compliant then it's going to send you a notification or take any
remediation action that you might have set. So it will assess audit evaluate the configuration of
resource with your organization policies and then take remediation. So in summary it looks at what
has changed from the resource configuration perspective is that resource still compliant with
organization policies. And it maintains the changelow and any remediation action that you might have
set. Come on the AWS console. So let me just search for AWS config.
Okay, now I'm on the AWS config. So if I just click on this dashboard you can see it's showing me
the compliance status. So I don't have a lot of resources or the rules. That's why it's showing
a zero compliant and zero non-compliant. But here is my resource inventory showing. So I have about
63 S3 buckets. And then I also have one config configuration recorder. Now if I go on the left
hand side if I just click on these rules and let me just click on add rules. So here it's asking
me select rule type. So you can either use add AWS managed rules or create your custom lambda
rule create custom rules using God. So I'll just show you some AWS managed rules. So the first one
here is access key is rotated. So it checks whether the active access keys are rotated. Then next one
you have the account part of organization. So this rule checks whether AWS account is part of the
AWS organization. So this how you can select the rules. And then I already showed you how it
takes a look at the inventory. So if I just click on this inventory and you can see it's showing me
all the resources that I have within this AWS account. And then what it will do is it will map
against the rules that we have created and see if there is non compliance. Okay hope it's clear on what
AWS config does. Now the next service AWS cloud trade. So cloud trade enables auditing security
monitoring and operational troubleshooting by tracking user activity and API usage. So now let's try
and understand this in a simple fashion. So what cloud trail monitors is if you're creating a new
AWS service, let's say you're creating an easy to instance or you're deleting an easy to instance
or you're creating a new S3 bucket deleting an S3 bucket. So it will track all the management events
for all your AWS resources within your account. And that would mainly
revolve around creating resources deleting resources and so on. Then cloud trail logs and
it generates logs continuously monitors and retains account activity related to actions across your
AWS infrastructure to enable compliance with regulations such as SOC, PCI and HIPAA. There might
be some compliance standards which dictate who can delete particular resource or who can create a
particular resource. So it helps enable compliance with those regulations. So in summary AWS cloud
trail focuses on who made the change and what changes were made to AWS resources.
Compared to if you look at AWS config, it looks at what has changed and is the resource still
compliant. Okay finally let's take a look at cloud watch. Amazon cloud watch is an AWS monitoring
service for cloud resources. Cloud watch is used to collect and track metrics collect and monitor
log files set alarms and dashboard. So cloud watch basically does three key things. One, it will collect
and track metrics related to AWS resources. Let's say you have created an EC2 instance which you
are using as a web server. Now we can track a metric like CPU utilization of the EC2 instance.
So it will collect and track that metric and if it goes beyond a threshold then it can
either alert or do some remediation action like launching another EC2 instance. The second thing
it does is it collects and monitors the log files. So all the logs that are generated by let's
say AWS Lambda EC2 S3. It will collect and monitor those log files and then finally you can set
alarms and also generate dashboard based on metrics and log files. Now from the exam
perspective it's very important you should understand what's the key difference between AWS
config, AWS cloud and cloud watch. Now let's assume the business has asked the IT team to create
an application like Amazon has created a web application such as www.amazon.com.
So the first thing that the developer will do is you will go to the AWS account and create
an EC2 instance and Amazon S3. Now in this scenario cloud trail is going to come into play
because it will record that someone created an EC2 instance, someone created an S3 bucket
or someone deleted an EC2 instance, someone deleted an S3 bucket. So all the management
activity would be tracked by cloud trail. Now let's say once we created this S3 bucket it did not
have public internet access. So the user were not able to access the images in this S3 bucket.
So they raised it as a defect with the developer and now developer has enabled public
internet access on this S3 bucket. But let's say security team had a policy which says
that if the S3 bucket is made public then it's a security compliance violation.
So this is where AWS config comes into play. So you might have created a rule
which said that if S3 bucket within your AWS account has a public internet access
that should show that the particular S3 bucket is non-compliant. So this is where AWS
config will come into play. It will evaluate all the AWS services against the rules that have
been defined and in this case now this S3 bucket has become non-compliant. So it will be
flagged by AWS config as non-compliant and then possibly take a remedial action.
Finally we have the AWS cloud watch. Now let's say all the issues have been resolved and this
web application is working great. Now the users have started accessing this application which is
hosted on easy to instance and there has been a lot of load because the number of users has
increased drastically. Now this web server is having performance issues. So in this case the
AWS cloud watch comes into play. So it can track the CPU utilization and many other
metrics for this easy to instance and if it reaches beyond a certain threshold then it can alert
or take some remediation action by adding another easy to instance. Similarly all the logs
generated let's say who access these easy to instance and many other details would be
captured in the cloud watch logs. So hopefully now the difference between
it was config cloud rail and cloud watch is clear to you, I will see in the next lecture.